我们该走了
We should go.
快到晚上了
Night is coming.
你知道的，他们站着睡觉
They sleep standing up, you know.
大象们
Elephants.
一旦倒下了，他们就无法再站起来
On account once laid down, they cannot rise again.
是这样的吗？
Is that so?
我还真是不知道
I was not aware.
我们该走了
We should go.
去哪儿？
Where?
尤地加离这儿不远
Utica is not far.
尤地加
Utica.
那儿有什么？
What's there for us?
掩蔽之处以及食物
Shelter. Food.
这两样我都不需要
I need neither.
那么，睡觉呢
Sleep, then.
睡觉还是不错的
Sleep would be pleasant.
那么…
So...
就去尤地加
Utica then.
天呐！
Dear me.
说真的，阿奎奈这里真是我们最好的选择了么
Really, Aquinas, is this the best we can do?
无所谓，无所谓
No matter. No matter.
弄点水，洗漱洗漱
Bring water for washing.
再整点面包…跟红酒
And bread... and wine.
我想今晚我要把自己灌醉
I think I shall make myself drunk tonight.
也许这一次你应该加入我
Perhaps just this once you will join me.
我不这么想
I think not.
精神点，我们还活着
Cheer up. We live.
是的，我们还活着
We do. We live.
只要还有生命，就有希望
And where there's life, there's hope.
我只是在想我们是否做成了任何事情，老朋友
I'm afraid if we have done anything, old friend,
我们的经历已经驳斥了那个谚语了
we've disproved that proverb.
阿奎奈，这块面包太硬了
Aquinas, this bread is stubborn.
把你的小刀给我
Give me your knife.
西比乌…
Scipio...
你具有隐忍的精神
you have a tolerant spirit.
如果你可以，你应该…
If you can, you should...
跟恺撒和平相处
make your peace with Caesar.
噢，我没想过那个，我应该跟着你干
Oh, I don't know about that. I shall do whatever you do.
我是不会那么做的
I wouldn't do that.
走你自己的路  不论怎样，我们别说这个了
Go your own way.  In any case, let's not discuss it now.
会有很多时间进行这种悲观的讨论的
There'll be plenty of time for such sad talk.
请原谅我
If you'll excuse me.
我要去小便
I need to urinate.
我相信那边有个小便的地方
There's a pisspot through there, I believe.
来人啊！来人啊！
Help! Help!
让他们都离开
Send them away.
现在动手吧
Do it now.
动作利索点，孩子
Cut deep, boy.
永别了，长官
Goodbye, sir.
我们非常感激
We thank you so much.
我们希望你们能够欣赏我们卑贱的努力
We hope you have enjoyed our humble efforts
在这样一个快乐的日子里！
on this happy day!
我们显赫的长辈归来的日子！
Happy day on which our glorious father has returned!
朱力安太阳升起的日子
Happy day on which the Julian sun has risen
让庞培的夜晚永远消失吧！
and banished Pompeian night forever!
我们勇敢的勇士回家的日子
Happy day on which our brave soldiers
能够跟他们的家人团聚！
have come home to their families!
快乐的日子！
Happy day!
你好  欢迎回来
Salve.  Welcome back.
这次回来再也不用走了吗？ 是的，是的
Are you home for good now?  I am. I am.
我再也不用出征了
No more soldiering for me.
太好了，亲爱的
Bona Dea.
真是很好，对吧？
It's nice, isn't it?
没错
It is.
这些是什么人？ 我在去年买了他们
Who are these?  I bought them last year.
我们现在有4个奴隶了？
Four slaves we have now?
当时他们的价格很优惠
They were a good price.
相对于一个战士的薪水来说？
On a soldier's wage?
肉店付的钱，而且还节余下来不少
The butcher shop paid for them with plenty to spare.
肉店？
The butcher shop?
莱蒂跟我弄了个不错的生意
Me and Lyde have made a nice business out of it.
有时候每周能够有500头
Five hundred head a week sometimes.
主要是猪，当然也有跟宗教交易的牛跟羊
Pigs mostly, but some sheep and cows for the religious trade.
艾瑞纳！
Eirene!
看见你真是太好了  主人，我也很高兴见到你
It's very good to see you.  It's good to see you too, master.
你说我们的语言！ 如果这能够让你高兴的话
You speak our words!  If it pleases you.
噢，当然，当然让我高兴
Oh, it does. Of course it does.
你想喝点什么吗？
Can I get you anything?
如果能有水的话就很好
A bit of water would be nice.
Ah!
我给你带了点东西
I brought you something.
这里，让我来
Here, let me.
真可爱
Lovely.
祭祖节在本月15号开始
"Parentalia begins on the ldes.
神殿将会关闭
Temples will be shut,
不会在其中举行庆典
and no wherein celebrated.
公众的欢庆将在竞技场第5小时开始
Public festivals shall be at the fifth hour in the circus.
卡比托奈山丘兄弟会将提供红酒，
Wine to be provided by the Capitoline fraternity,
磨坊行会将会提供面包
and cakes by the Guild of Millers.
磨坊行会仅使用最好的谷物
The Guild of Millers uses only the finest grains--
真正的罗马面包给真正的罗马人
True Roman bread, for true Romans."
那个又老又肥的婊子，对吧？
The fat old bitch herself eh?
回家的感觉肯定很好
Must be good to be home.
大概，你已经离开了两年了？
What is it, two years you've been gone?
你还在跟我妈妈上床吗？
Are you still fucking my mother?
当她想要我的时候
When she'll have me.
怪不得你好像什么都知道
That would explain your excessive familiarity.
对不起  没什么
Excuse me.  That's all right.
我只是好奇 而且你是对的
I was merely curious, and you're correct.
回家的感觉真好
It does feel good to be home.
我亲爱的儿子
My darling boy.
还是这么帅
So handsome.
姐姐，希望你都还好  让我拥抱你
Sister, I hope you're well.  Let me hug you.
进去洗洗
Come inside and wash.
把你身上那种马的臭味洗掉
Let's get rid of the stink of horse off you.
泰门，我会，晚点再见你的
Timon, I'll, uh... see you later.
快点，母亲，我们会迟到的
Please, Mother, we will be late.
哦，我们不能迟到，迟到是永远都无法接受的
Oh, we must not be late. That would never do.
我并不想去参加晚宴，正如你一样
I do not want to go to dinner any more than you do,
但是恺撒对我真是太好了
but Caesar has treated me extremely well,
所有如果被邀请我们就要去
and we must go if asked.
荣耀的请求…  荣耀？
Honor demands--  Honor?
荣耀  那么就不荣耀
Honor.  Not honor then,
只是常识
common sense.
我无法要求恺撒的宽恕
I cannot ask mercy of Caesar,
接受他的任命以及宠爱之后
accept rank and favor from him,
再拒绝他的友谊
and then refuse his friendship.
什么样的男人才会一开始就请求宽恕？
What sort of man asks for mercy in the first place?
我可以告诉你，母亲
I assure you, Mother,
我不为自己感到自豪
I am not proud of myself.
我根本一点都不自豪
I am not proud at all.
在贵族们自取灭亡的那种场合
In lieu of a noble suicide,
你应该感到满足了
you shall have to be content with that.
把我的围巾拿来
Bring me my shawl.
请不要去了
Please, do not come.
我会向阿提娅解释的
I shall make your excuses to Atia.
当然不行，我要去
Certainly not. I will go.
缺席将会被看成软弱的表现
Not to be there would be seen as weakness.
或许去看他对你也有好处
Perhaps it will do you good to see him.
他只是个人
See that he is just a man.
失去他的爱情并不值得你
The loss of his affection is not worth
无尽的愤怒以及悲伤
this endless raging sorrow.
我既不感到愤怒也不感到悲伤
I feel neither rage nor sorrow.
我对于恺撒的异议完全是基于政治的
My objection to Caesar is purely political,
而不是个人感情的
not personal.
庞提克军队跑得如此快
The Pontic troops ran so fast
我都不知道他们是否曾经停下来过
I don't know if they ever stopped.
怪不得庞培如此轻松的就把庞提克拿下了
It is no wonder Pompey took Pontius so readily.
一个拿着棍子的小孩或许都可以做到
A child with a stick might have done so.
那么下一个目标是什么呢，长官？日尔曼，有可能吗？
What next, sir? Germany perhaps?
恐怕下个月我就必须加上一场盛典
I'm afraid I must put on a triumph this next month,
让那些该死的畜生们来安排
and they're damnable beasts to organize.
人们喜欢胜利的检阅
Still, the people love a good parade
那么我们就不能让他们失望
and we must not disappoint them.
看见你们两个真是太好了
How lovely to see you both.
真的是太久了  我们很高兴能来这里
It's been far too long.  We are joyful to be here.
很高兴，真的  这是用于葬礼的围巾吗？
Joyful, indeed.  Is this a mourning shawl?
很漂亮，有什么人死了吗？
It's very pretty. Has someone died?
有很多人都死了
Agreatmanyhavedied.
没错，但是现在一切都结束了
How true. But it's all over now,
而且我们还活着，嗯？
and we're still alive, neh?
这真是不可能，屋大维？
It's not possible. Octavian?
天哪，你让我感觉自己很老
Gods, you make me feel old.
来
Come.
大概有四个人那么高
It is the height of four men,
还有一个长长的像鹅一样的脖子
with a long neck like a goose,
像豹子那样的斑点像马一般的速度
spots like a leopard, and the speed of a horse.
我不信，又是个什么狮头，羊身，蛇尾的怪物
I don't believe it. A new Chimera.
我向你保证这绝对是真的
I assure you, it is quite real.
走运的话，你可以在我的盛典上看到一个
With any luck, you may see one at my triumph.
几个月前我就试着弄一头过来，
I have been trying to bring one over for months now,
但是那种可怜的动物不断的在路途上死亡
but the wretched creatures keep dying on the way here.
他们不喜欢大海  听起来真是够累了
They do not like the sea.  It all sounds very tiring.
这个万恶的盛典结束后
After this infernal triumph is done
你一定要到乡下修养  我也有这么想
you must go to the country and relax.  I should like that,
但是盛典之后我就要开始认真的工作了
but then my work begins in earnest.
我必须提出归权于共和
I must set about putting the Republic to rights.
非常好的想法，你打算怎么进行？有想过吗
Splendid notion. How shall you proceed, do you suppose?
我有几个想法，但是我还是乐于听取意见
I have a few ideas, but I am open to suggestion.
昨天，我看到马其奥那个面包师在一堆垃圾里面
Yesterday, I saw Malchio the baker in a litter.
一个面包师！我不得不立刻中止这种事情
A baker! I'd put a stop to that sort of thing immediately.
我会关注这件事情的
I shall have it looked into.
屋大维？
Octavian?  Hmm?
如果你是我的话，你会如何进行？
How would you proceed, were you me?
嗯，进行什么？  归权于共和
Uh, proceed with?  Putting the Republic to rights.
如何进行
how to proceed.
我会开始一个有关公众工作的大型项目
I would start a large program of public works--
雇佣公民跟自由人
employ citizens and free men,
维修排水管道河坝之类的工作
repair the aqueducts, levee the river- that sort of thing.
我会增加最少100个以上新的元老
I would create at least 100 or so new senators,
这样我就可以确认他们是我的人而不是我隐秘的敌人
that I could be sure were my creatures rather than my secret enemies.
屋大维，你到底想说什么？
What is your point, Octavian?
我不是说你布鲁图斯，你是个值得尊敬的人
I did not mean you, Brutus, you're a man of honor.
我相信你的投诚是真诚的
I believe that your capitulation is sincere.
你能这么说真好
How nice of you to say so.
我刚刚有个想法
I just had a thought.
你是不是有个叫艾黎奥斯希克拉丝手下最近才死？
Did not your man Aelius Siculus die recently?
恐怕是这样的事实上死在萨泊萨斯
I'm afraid he did. In Thapsus, in fact.
那样的话你应该取代他成为一个大祭司
Just so. You shall take his seat at the pontiff's table.
大祭司？太年轻？
Pontiff? So young?
我进入长老院的时候
I was not so much older
我也不是很老  没错，但是…
when I entered the college.  very true, but--
我相信我有权
I believe I have the authority
指派我想安排的人  绝对没错
to appoint whom I like.  lndeed, yes.
这真是莫大的荣耀，快亲吻你舅公的手
This is a great honor. Kiss your uncle's hand.
我可以亲吻您的手，舅公，但是我做不好一个祭司
I kiss your hand, Uncle, but truly I would make an ill pontiff.
别胡说八道，你会成为一个好祭司的
Don't be ridiculous. You'll make a lovely pontiff.
你会照应的，对吧？
You'll see to it, right?
我宁可集中精神于诗歌
I had rather thought to concentrate on my poetry for a while.
他会成为一个好祭司的  诗歌可以慢慢再说
He'll make a lovely pontiff.  Poetry can wait.
但是不耽搁太久
It should not wait too long.
诗歌是属于年轻人的
Poetry is a young man's calling...
你不认为吗？
don't you think?
我们在这里，萨泊萨斯的城墙就在身后
There's us with the walls of Thapsus at our backs
你老爸也就在这里
and your father was just here.
他们所有的军团，骑兵
Now coming towards us on the plain
还有900头战象
with all their legions, cavalry
直接冲向我们
and 900 war elephants,
我的老天爷啊
Scipio and Juno.
“紧紧的稳住”恺撒说 “让这帮混蛋们冲过来！”
"Hold fast," says General Caesar, "let the bastards come!"
让我来  请不要这样，主人
I'll do it.  Please, don't, master.
这是我的工作，女主人会生气的
This is my work. Lady will be angry.
谁才是主人，嗯？
Who's master, eh?
投石机架在城墙上，而且锋线的士兵认为
...ballistas on the city walls, and the front line thinks
他们听到了前进的口令，于是在长官可以停止他们之前
they've heard the order to advance, so before the officers can stop it,
所有的部队以双倍的速度冲向了西比乌的手下
the whole fucking army charges on Scipio's men double tempo.
此时，战象们…
Now, the elephants--
看到我们边跑边狂叫
elephants see us come running and screaming
他们居然转了个头冲向自己的队伍了
and they turn tail and charge on their own lines--
砰！一片混乱！
boom! Chaos!
噢，别哭，只是个游戏
Oh, don't cry, it was just a game.
一天无所事事坐在这里，你肯定很无聊
You must be bored, sitting around here all day.
我并没有这样感觉
I don't mind it.
你们已经退伍一个月了  我知道
You've been discharged a month.  I know.
我并没有催促的意思，钱以及其他事情都还好
I mean, there's no hurry. We're all right for money and everything--
但是我不能永远无所事事的混着
But I can't be loafing around here forever.
那么你不想从事肉店的买卖？
So you don't want to take up the butchering trade?
管理店务？！
Shopkeeping?!
起码你能够有点事情可做
It will give you something to do.
对于军官真是个好工作，呵？
This is fine work for a prefect, eh?
味道就像回到过去的老时光  没错
Smells like old times.  It does that.
你还记得在阿瓦砾卡的那次围城吗？
You remember that little siege at Avaricum?
坐在门槛上可对生意没有什么帮助
You'll not learn a trade sitting on your pugas.
还有好多被宰杀的牲畜需要挂起来呢
There's plenty more carcasses to be hung.
明天，你明天久能够拿回你的钱！
Tomorrow! You'll have your money tomorrow!
把他的鼻子割下来  不，别这样…
Let's take his nose off.  No, not me no--
嗨，住手！
Don't- don't fuss.  Hey, stop that!
到别的地方去做这种事
Take your business elsewhere.
干你屁事，你个混蛋？ 会影响我的生意
What's it to you, you bastard?  It's bad for trade.
你他妈的是谁，小个子？
And who the fuck are you, little man?
我是卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯， 我认得你
I am Lucius vorenus,  I know you.
大兵哥，对吧？住在染厂那边，有个漂亮的媳妇
Soldier boy, isn't it? Up by the dyeworks, tasty wife.
少扯我的老婆
Do not speak of my wife.
快走，这是命令
Get gone. That's an order.
不不不，命令，命令？不不不
No no no. Orders? Orders? No no no.
你现在不是士兵了，你只不过是个他妈的看店的店员
You're not a soldier now. You're a fucking shopkeeper's clerk.
你死定了，你死定了  现在就离开
You're dead, you are.  Walk away now
以后也不要让我在这条街上看见你
and do not let me see you on this street again.
你们两个都死定了
Both of you... dead.
都别看了，忙你们自己的事吧
Get back to your business.
你不应该这么做的
You shouldn't have done that.
他们是伊拉斯特斯·弗尔曼的手下
Those were Erastes Fulmen's people.
对于他的不敬，他不会就这么算了
He won't take disrespect like that.
你打了他  没什么大不了
You hit him.  It was nothing.
伊拉斯特斯·弗尔曼会杀了你的
Erastes Fulmen will kill you.
他只是个骗子  他过去是的
He's just a crook.  He used to be.
但是自从庞培的手下走后他就掌控了这一带
Since Pompey's gangs left he's had the run of the hill.
他现在是大人物了
He's a big man now.
他可以杀掉任何他想杀的人！
He kills whoever he wants!
我可不是一个可以被随意辱骂的穷人！
I'm no prole to be abused!
我可是军团里面的前任军官！
I was prefect in the Evocati!
恺撒亲自赠送过一匹马给我
Caesar himself gave me a horse.
感谢你，先生
Thank you, sir.
我希望那顿晚餐没有给你带来过多的痛苦
I hope that dinner was not too painful for you.
哦，我已经习惯痛苦了，我根本就不介意
Oh, I'm used to pain. I don't mind it.
我真希望你以前不是那么在乎他
I wish you didn't care for him so much.
我真希望我以前不是那么在乎你
I wish I didn't care for you so much.
别说了
Stop.
你的那个弟弟已经变成了一个动人的男人
That brother of yours has become quite the pretty man.
恺撒似乎很喜欢他
Caesar seems very fond of him.
非常
very much.
母亲说恺撒把他看成情人，
Mother claims Caesar took him for a lover.
真的吗？
Really?
厨子说她听见他们在壁橱里面…
The cook said she heard them going at it in a closet.
屋大维坚持说那并不是事实
Octavian insisted it was not so.
他说厨娘听见的声音是
He said the noises she heard were
恺撒遭受惊人痛苦时发出的声音
some terrible affliction of Caesar's.
母亲根本不信，只要她相信了什么…
Mother wouldn't have it. Once she gets an idea--
痛苦？什么痛苦？
Affliction? What affliction?
我不知道  他没有说吗？
I don't know.  Did he not say?
他发誓要保密的
He was sworn to secrecy.
但是他说惊人的？他说了惊人的痛苦？
But he said terrible? He said terrible affliction?
你必须要找出到底这种痛苦是什么
You must find out exactly what this affliction is.
你必须要找出神到底对他进行了什么诅咒
You must find out which god has cursed him.
我怎么能做到？那是个秘密
How can I do that? It's a secret.
你必须要找出来，这是我在寻找的武器
You must find it out. This is the weapon I seek.
加上神的帮助，我就可以毁灭他
With the god's help, I can destroy him.
请不要这么说
Please don't talk this way.
你想要我对你说谎？
Would you rather I lied to you?
我宁愿你想些别的东西
I would rather that you think of something
而不是如何毁灭我的舅公
other than the destruction of my uncle.
我从来没有骗过你
I have never lied to you.
他对我还是有很大的掌控
He still has some terrible hold over me.
我不希望如此，但是他不肯就此算了
I wish it were not so, but he will not let go.
你会问你的弟弟吗？
Will you ask your brother?
那会让你高兴吗？
Would that make you happy?
是的，会的
Yes, it would.
你在看什么？
What are you reading?
一个对于奇观解释的导论
A guide to the interpretation of prodigies.
好看吗？
Is it good?
除了概念外，很闷
It's dull beyond conception.
如果我要成为一个祭司，我必须要熟悉他们无稽的行话
If I am to be a pontiff, I must be familiar with their ludicrous jargon.
不能让舅公失望  不能让舅公失望
Mustn't let down Uncle.  Mustn't let down Uncle.
我很无聊
I'm bored.
我可以读给你听  如果你想的话
I could read to you.  If you like.
小麻雀，我的爱就是爱
"Little sparrow, my love is love,
跟她玩耍的人允许她躺在大腿上
with whom she plays, permits to lie within her lap,
捏捏她的爪子，咬咬她的啄
to nip her finger, biting quickly with that bill,
我应该像她一样跟你玩耍来抚平我杂乱的心
I should like to play with you as she and soothe my troubled heart."
很好  你不喜欢？
very nice.  You do not like it?
不，你朗诵的很好，但是…
No, you recite well, but...
我只是对于诗歌厌烦了
I'm tired of poetry.
跟我说个秘密  秘密？
Tell me a secret.  A secret?
一个令人震惊而又危险无人知道的秘密
Something shocking and dangerous that nobody knows.
我可不知道那种秘密
I don't know any secrets like that.
我知道
I know.
那么说说恺撒跟他的神秘的病痛如何？
What about Caesar and his mysterious affliction?
什么病痛？
What affliction?
别撒谎，就是你跟母亲说的那个
Don't lie. The one you told Mother about.
噢，没那回事，我瞎编的
Oh, it was nothing. I was just making it up.
那么你们是情人？ 当然不是了
So you were lovers?  Of course not.
要不你们就是情侣，要不，就是神对于恺撒的诅咒，到底是哪个？
Either you were lovers, or some god has cursed Caesar, which is it?
姐姐，根本没有神 别变得那么令人讨厌
Sister, there are no gods.  Don't be horrid.
毫无疑问的，一个某种八卦的散布者
There is doubtless a Prime Mover of some sort,
但是在我们这个圈子里对于像我们这样的人试图打探八卦？
but a community of beings that look like us and meddle in our affairs?
似乎是不现实的  你不信任我
Highly improbable.  You don't trust me.
我相信你，你是我最亲爱的人
I do trust you. You are my dearest friend.
那么就告诉我！ 为什么一定要知道这个？
Then tell me!  Why this in particular?
为什么你会在意恺撒是否有病痛？
Why do you care if Caesar has an affliction?
我可不在乎什么小细节
I don't care the slightest bit.
我只想知道一个大秘密，一个值得一听的东西
Only that it would be a terrible secret and something worth hearing.
而且我怀疑你是否有什么惊人秘密能够
And I doubt very much that you have any terrible secrets
值得你说出来的
of your own worth telling.
你的怀疑是错误的  哦，是吗，那么是什么秘密呢？
You'd be wrong.  Oh please, like what?
我曾经拷打并且杀死了一个人  骗子
I've tortured and killed a man.  Liar.
你还记得卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯？
Do you remember Lucius vorenus?
一个在高卢救了我的战士？
One of the soldiers who rescued me in Gaul?
你杀了他？ 当然没有
You killed him?  Of course not.
他有个老婆红杏出墙
He has a wife who deceived him.
那个他认为是他女儿的孩子，其实
A child he thinks is his daughter's son is in fact
是他老婆跟一个低贱的半希腊血统的屠夫的孩子
his wife's child by a low half-Greek butcher.
真是太肮脏了
How sordid.
那个屠夫是我杀的，或者说协从杀的
It was the butcher I killed. Helped kill, anyway.
噢，我想，应该很精彩
Oh. Bravo, I suppose.
你自己想要知道一个惊人秘密的
You asked for a terrible secret.
再说一个
Try again.
什么？
What?
让路，让路
Get out of the way!
百夫长！
Centurion!
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯！
Lucius Vorenus!
内奥比，还是像以前那么可爱
Niobe, looking as lovely as ever.
菲利斯献上她的致意
Phyllis sends her best regards.
你的家人真漂亮
very pretty family you have.
这么久之后能够见到你真是太好了
It's good to see you again after so long.
嗯，打完仗回来了
So, back from the wars.
平民生活，呃？
Civilian life, eh?
肯定很难适应
Must be hard to adjust.
不同的规则
Different rules.
他妈的不同的规矩！
Different fucking rules!
我的手下阿宝说你打了他的脸
My man Urbo here says you slapped him in the face.
你那么做了吗？ 是的
Did you do that?  I did.
完美的例子…不同的规矩
Perfect example- different rules.
你要明白，我有权能够惩罚我的手下
You see, I'm allowed to chastise my people.
像你这样的平头老百姓是不允许碰他的
Regular citizens like you are not allowed to touch them.
如果有人那么做了，那么他就要被惩罚
If someone does touch them, they have to be punished.
这就是规矩
Rules.
你到底想说什么
Get to your point.
这已经是第二次了，卢西尔斯，乌瑞纳斯
This is the second time that Lucius vorenus
显示了对我的不敬
has shown me disrespect.
下一个集市日的中午
Next market day at noon,
他会在市场上找到我
he will find me in the Forum.
他会跪倒在我面前
He will kneel down before me.
他会亲吻我的脚并且向我道歉
He will kiss my feet and he will apologize to me.
如果他不这么做的话我会回到这里把他杀了
If he does not do this, I will come here and kill him.
但是他死之前，他会看到他的老婆跟女儿被强奸
But before he dies, he will see his wife and daughters raped.
然后我会烧了这栋房子
And then I will burn down this building.
等等
Hold.
你说完了？  是的
You've said your piece?  I have.
那么现在就离开吧
Then leave now.
祝你日安
Good day to you.
那么卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯的老婆是个婊子，跟我有何关系
So the wife of this Lucius vorenus is a whore. What's that to me?
很抱歉，这就是他所知道的了
I'm sorry, that's all he told me.
他发誓恺撒没有病痛  他在撒谎
He swears Caesar has no affliction.  He's lying.
那么就是我做的还不够了？
Is it not enough then?
如果恺撒有病痛
If Caesar has an affliction,
他就会因此而痛苦，无论你是否知道
he has it and suffers, whether you know it or not.
他在受罪，但是他还没有被毁灭
He suffers, but he is not destroyed.
你必须要回到你弟弟那里，从他的嘴里得到真相
You must go back to your brother and get the truth from him.
怎样做呢？我已经试过了  再试试
How? I tried.  Try again.
答应他一些东西
Promise him something.
你肯定有他想要的东西
You do have something he wants.
你是什么意思？
What do you mean?
一个年轻人会告诉他的爱人任何事情
A young man will tell his lover anything.
你肯定是在开玩笑
You can't be serious.
你怎么能…？
How can you...?
你知道他想要你
You know he wants you.
我就会背叛我的母亲
I would be betraying my brother.
我就会背叛我的家族
I would be betraying my family.
你的家族是满是毒蛇的蛇巢
Your family is a nest of snakes.
你对你的家族没有任何义务
You have no obligations to them.
他们是我的家人，他们爱我，我…
They are my family! They love me, l--
像我爱你那样
As I love you.
你把这个称作爱？
You call this love?
我不能
I can't.
你去哪里？ 回家
Where are you going?  Home.
别走
Don't go.
你母亲杀了格雷毕斯！
Your mother killed Glabius!
我的手下抓住了杀他的一个人
My people caught one of the men that did it.
一个泰门手下的人
One of Timon's men.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
听莱蒂的话  妈妈，请跟我们一起走
Do as Lyde says.  Please, Mama, come with us.
我要跟着你的父亲
My place is here with your father.
但是如果你被杀了呢？
But what if you're killed?
那么你们必须呆在乡下，不要回到城里
Then you must stay in the country, don't come back to the city.
你明白了吗？
You understand?
别回来，你会成为一个乡下的姑娘
Don't come back! You'll be country girls. Mm-hmm?
你的表亲会给你找个又好又英俊的农夫的
Your cousin will find you good handsome farmers to marry.
去向神们祈求保佑
Go ask the gods for blessing.
你不能让乌瑞纳斯去请求原谅？
Can't you get vorenus to do as Erastes asks?
如果你求他的话…
If you begged him--
去亲吻一个男人的脚？
To kiss a man's feet?
我永远不会求他这么做，而且他永远也不会这么做
I'd never ask such a thing, and he'd never agree to it.
永远记住你们是乌瑞纳斯家族的孩子
Always remember that you are children of the vorenii,
一个古老而且值得尊敬的名字
an old and respected name.
永远记住我们爱你
And always remember that we love you.
我非常爱你们，现在走吧
I love you very much. Now go on.
走，走
Go, go.
再见，姐姐
Goodbye, sister.
艾瑞纳你不打算把桌子收拾一下吗？
Eirene, are you going to leave this mess on the table?
内奥比，求你了，跟他们一起走吧
Please, Niobe, please, go with them.
我不会走的，别再让我走了
I will not and stop asking.
这个面包不错
Good bread this.
我买了比较好的那种
I bought the better kind.
还是取决于价格，对吧？
Hang the expense, eh?
滚开，都让路
Get back. Make way there.
快跑到个地方躲起来
Run and hide.
执政官大人 盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
Here comes the Consul Gaius Julius Caesar,
维纳斯之子，盖尔军团的统帅驾到
Son of venus, lmperator of the Gaelic Legions.
你好卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Salve, Lucius vorenus.
你的妻子很漂亮
Your wife is very beautiful.
她的名字是？
Her name?
内奥比，长官
Niobe, sir.
站起来 内奥比
Rise, Niobe.
我们能够有幸让你喝一口我们家里的水吗？
Would you honor us by drinking our water, sir?
很好
I'm happy to do so.
请坐下
Please, sit.
我总是给予你很高的敬意，乌瑞纳斯
I have always held you in high regard, vorenus,
而且我被告知你很受到你手下的尊重
and I am told you are a man of respect among your people here.
我希望如此  是这样的我来这里是想要你
I hope so.  That being so, I've come to ask you
代表我去做低地的地方长官
to stand for magistrate of Lower Aventine on my slate.
谢谢
Thank you.
那么？
Well?
您的到场给了我极大的荣耀，极大的荣耀
I am deeply honored by your presence here, sir, deeply honored.
但是…我不得不尊敬的表示拒绝
But... respectfully, I must decline.
那么，你还是对于我的行为感到不赞同？
So you still disapprove of my actions?
长官，毫无冒犯之意
Sir, with respect,
您的政治观点跟我的不同
your politics are not mine.
我知道这个
I am aware of that.
如果我是个地方长官的话我将不得不表述
Were I a magistrate, I would have to speak.
你将不会表述你对
And you will not speak
专制的好感？
in favor of a tyrant?
我不会说违背我信仰的话的
I will not speak against my beliefs.
味道不错
Delicious.
你错误判断了我…我不是个暴君
You misjudge me. I am no tyrant.
我合法的取得了独裁的权力
I have taken dictator's powers legally.
而且我将会把这些权力归还给人民以及元老们
And I will return those powers to the people and the senate
尽我最快的可能而且除非罗马恢复到它黄金岁月的
as soon as I am able. I will not rest
情况，我是不会休息的
until Rome is as it was in the golden age.
我无法独自进行下去，你会加入我吗？
I cannot succeed alone. Will you join me?
恺撒，万岁！万岁！
Hail Caesar! Hail!
恺撒，万岁！
Hail Caesar!
恺撒，恺撒，恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
Alittle more, Ithink.
No, the sleeves are fine, leave those alone.
You just be careful what you're doing with that pin.
Yes. Now, if you could go around the side--
at the hem, at the bottom--
that needs taking up a little bit there.
There. No, that's fine.
I don't know. That just isn't working for me.
你在找什么吗？
Were you looking for anything in particular?
呃…并不是
Oh... not really.
你有什么好笑的事情吗？
Do you have anything comical?
嗯，我想是没有
Um, I don't think so.
你
You.
为什么让他走？这儿很热
Why send him away? It's hot.
我不喜欢他看我
I don't like that one. He looks at me.
是吗？让卡斯特教训他
Does he? Have Castor beat him.
可能我会这么做
Maybe I will.
我叫另外一个过来  别
I'll call for another one.  Don't.
单独呆在一起很好啊
It's nice to be alone.
是吗？
Isn't it?
我猜是吧  过来跟我躺在一起
I suppose.  Come lie down with me.
跟你躺在一起？为什么？
Lie down with you? Why?
你会喜欢的
I would like it.
为什么？ 为什么不会？
Why?  Why not?
我可以想到好几个原因
I can think of several reasons.
你小的时候每晚都跑到我的床上
When you were little, you would come to my bed every night.
不是每晚，只是在我害怕的时候
Not every night. Only when I was scared.
你总是很害怕
You were scared a great deal.
我现在不害怕
I'm not scared now.
假装  我可不善于假装
Pretend.  I have no skill at pretending.
我现在很困窘
I'm embarrassed now.
我以为你想要我
I thought you wanted me.
你是个男人了，对吧？
You're a man now, aren't you?
你可以任取所求
You can take what you want.
弟弟，告诉我一件事
Brother, tell me something...
唉
Ah.
唉是什么意思？
What do you mean, "Ah"?
现在就是回报时间了
Now comes the price.
你是什么意思？ 你是个有道德的女人
What do you mean?  You're a virtuous woman,
那么你应该知道诱惑你弟弟是一个错误
so you must know that seducing your own brother is wrong.
你跟我已经越过了那个卑微的社会习俗
You and I are above such petty social convention.
但是乱伦不仅仅是违背了社会习俗
But incest is not merely wrong by convention.
它从本质上就是错的，错的
It's wrong in essence. It must be,
否则的话，为什么乱伦者的孩子里面有那么多的白痴跟怪胎？
else why so many idiots and monsters among the children of incest?
别  别担心
Don't.  Don't worry.
我不太可能会让你怀孕
It's unlikely I've seeded you.
不是在满月的时候
Not with the moon in transit.
关键在于，你不是个为了肉欲能够做这种错事的女人
The point is, you're not the woman to do such wrong out of mere lust.
所以，你肯定有其他的企图
Ergo, you must have another purpose.
我猜你应该是对恺撒的健康又有了新的非常奇怪的兴趣吧
I suspect you shall renew your strange interest in Caesar's health.
我…我都做了什么？我都做了什么？
Wha- what have I done? What have I done?
我都做了什么？什么？
What have I done? What?
你都做了什么？告诉我
What have you done? Tell me.
答应我
Promise.
答应我你不会跟母亲说
Promise you won't tell Mother.
看看你
Look at you.
你看起来就像要洗的衣服
You look like laundry.
那里
There.
看起来还可以吗
Does it look well?  very well.
非常好
It feels strange.
感觉很奇怪
不，别，你会弄脏它的
No, don't, you'll dirty it.
从后面看好看吗
Does it hang properly at the back?
我也这么认为
I think so.
冷静，母亲，说真的
Calm down, Mother, really.
冷静？我还没有开始发火呢
Calm down? I have not even begun to get angry!
够了
Enough!
我是你儿子，不再是孩子了
I am your son but not your child.
你不能再打我了  我不能？
You will not strike me anymore.  Will I not?
你干了你姐姐，你这个变态！
You fucked your sister, you little pervert!
别跟我说什么可以，什么不可以做！
Don't tell me what I will and will not do!
都住口！！  你敢吗
Be quiet!!  You wouldn't dare.
你们怎么能做这样的事情？
How could you do this to me?
我自己的孩子
My own child.
你杀了我丈夫  我跟你说过，不是吗？
You killed my husband.  I told you, didn't l?
我跟你说过 我没有杀他！ 你在撒谎
I told you I didn't kill him!  You're a liar.
赛维莉娅抓住了动手的一个人
Servilia caught one of the men that did it.
一个泰门的手下  那么那个人在哪里？
One of Timon's men.  And where is this man?
你亲自问过他吗？
Did you speak to him?
看着我，看着我！
Look at me. Look at me!
我以先祖的名义发誓
I swear on the spirits of my ancestors,
朱庇特可以为证，我没有杀你的丈夫！
on the stone of Jupiter, I did not kill your husband!
你为了个谎言而作践自己！
You abased yourself for a stupid lie!
我不知道  赛维莉娅才是骗子，你这个蠢人！
I don't know.  Servilia is the liar, you fool!
她骗你来跟我作对
She lied to turn you against me.
我可怜的小羔羊
My poor lamb.
艾瑞纳？
Eirene?
艾瑞纳！
Eirene!
来了，主人
Coming, master.
坐下来跟我一起喝两口
Sit down. Have a drink with me.
你的头发跟我母亲的很像
My mother had hair like yours.
虽然眼睛是灰色的
Grey eyes though.
大大的灰色的眼睛
Big grey eyes.
奴隶…在北边的一块农场
Slave... on one of those farms up north.
闻起来有松树的味道
Smelled of pine trees.
大概工作在木场里
Worked in the wood yards, probably.
我想这就是为什么闻起来有松树的味道
That's what I think. Explains the pine smell.
不知道我父亲是谁
Don't know who my father was.
可能就是另外一个奴隶而已
Just another slave probably.
一些胆小的混球都敢骑在他的头上拉屎
Some timid cunt shoveling shit with a collar around his neck
因为他没有男人应有的勇气
because he didn't have the courage to die like a man.
如果让我向任何人屈膝
I'd cut my fucking heart out of my chest
我会挖出我的心脏然后吃点它
and eat it before I knelt down to anybody!
混蛋！ 安静！
Cunt!  Quiet!
小声点！
Keep it down!
都去死吧，你们这帮混蛋
Suck my cock, the lot of youse!
我是泰特斯·波罗对吧？
I'm Titus Pullo, right?
没错吧？
Right?
没错，主人
Right, master.
你是个好姑娘
You're a good girl.
但是你不常笑
You don't smile much though.
你想要我笑？
You want me to smile?
我想要你开心
I want you to be happy.
这样好多了
That's better.
喝点酒
Have some wine.
到这来
Come here.
Closer.
脱掉你的衣服
Take off your dress.
为什么戴帽子？
What's the hat for?
赎罪日
Yom Kippur.
噢，是今天吗？
Oh, is that today?
你也称自己是犹太人？
You call yourself a Jew?
怎么，你现在要当我的老师？
What, are you my Rebbe now?
让路，让路！ 动手！
Move! Move!  vos!
不！
No!
快，抓住她！
Quick, grab her!
扒光她！
Strip her!
不！不！
No! No!
谁来帮帮她！
Somebody help her!
来救救我
救我，保护我，救我，保护我
...keep and protect me. Keep and protect me.
来救我，来救救我，保护我
不！
Keep and protect me. No!
我们走！
Let's go!
翻译:TLF字幕组